all right
[Music]
in my video on antibiotic resistant
genes I explored how more were found in
the guts of those who eat meat Dairy and
eggs than those who eat completely
plant-based but does the transfer of
bacteria from animal Foods in the human
gut result in differences in actual
clinical outcomes other than food
poisoning of course foodborne bacteria
is taking about 350 million people every
year most of that can be traced to meat
dairy products and eggs besides food
poisoning though what about extra
intestinal infections infections outside
the digestive tract for example due to
pathogenic and antibiotic resistant E
coli from retail chicken breasts
infections where though
the urinary tract
there's a type of E coli called st131
which is a food-borne uropathogen
meaning it causes urinary tract
infections most of which are just
bladder infections which typically
amount to little more than a painful
annoyance but can become invasive and
spread up into the kidneys and invade
the bloodstream and end your life
e coliast131 emerged explosively in the
last 20 years or so to become the most
important multi-drug resistant
uropathogen in circulation today
urinary tract infections are caused
principally by ascending E coli
infection via an intestine stool
urethra root meaning these E coli that
cause UTIs called extra intestinal
pathogenic E coli or expect bacteria
start out in the colon make it to the
anus and then make their way up into the
urethra then into your bladder how do
they get into your intestines in the
first place
that's where the chicken comes in the
role of poultry meat can be to introduce
the expect bacteria allowing it to
colonize the rectums of consumers lying
in wait until an opportunity to cause
infection presents itself for example
thrusting from sexual intercourse can
introduce the bacteria into the urethra
the time lag between human expect
acquisition in the intestine and the
bladder infection has been the
fundamental challenge linking the two
but we now have strong evidence the
substantial portion of the st-131
strains infecting humans originate from
poultry but they couldn't tell whether
any single infection arose from direct
exposure to contaminated poultry or
indirectly from chicken meat from Human
to human transmission from say a partner
who ate some contaminated poultry
what percentage of human UTIs arise from
poultry researchers analyzed E coli
isolates from urine samples from
patients with suspected UTIs and
compared them to the bacteria on retail
meat samples in the same region using
DNA fingerprinting techniques they found
that about a fifth of E coli isolates
from suspected cases of UTIs belong to
types found in local retail poultry
21 might not sound like a lot but E coli
UTIs are one of the most common
infectious diseases in the United States
affecting approximately 7 million women
so contaminated chicken may result in
more than a million UTIs in American
women every year
this may explain why women infected with
multi-drug resistant E coli reported
more frequent chicken consumption
putting them at nearly four times the
odds the frequent consumption of pork
was also a risk factor wait is it found
in pigs Too Human expect those extra
intestinal E coli that cause UTIs have
also been identified on pig farms in
pigs and in retail pork meat albeit at a
considerably lower levels than in
poultry or chicken meat so chicken is
riskiest pork less so and beef could be
considered the safest from a UTI
standpoint Since cattle don't appear to
be a reservoir of these particular types
of E coli okay well if meat including
poultry and pork is the major reservoir
for these UTI bacteria than vegetarians
who avoid meat should theoretically
suffer less exposure however no study
thus far has examined whether vegetarian
diets reduce the risk of UTIs
until now a prospective study on the
risk of urinary tract infection in
vegetarians versus non-vegetarians well
if around 20 percent are tied to retail
chicken meat no surprise that eating
vegetarian is associated with around 20
lower risk of UTIs particularly in women
and this Association was independent of
diseases and predisposing risk factors
like hypertension diabetes and high
cholesterol meaning it's not just due to
the fact that vegetarians had less
diabetes or something
what about buying organic chicken
bacteria swab from chicken labeled
organic harbored less antibiotic
resistant bacteria but no no less likely
to be contaminated with expect UTI
bacteria these findings suggest that
retail chicken products in the United
States even if they're labeled organic
pose a potential Health threat to
Consumers because they're contaminated
with extensively antibiotic resistant E
coli including the ones that cause UTIs
to date only the Jack-in-the-Box E coli
like 015787 are considered food
adulterants meaning it's not legal to
knowingly sell contaminated meat why
don't they do the same with the expect
bugs now that they're such strong
evidence they're infecting so many women
well on a survey of retail chicken
breasts collected widely across the
United States 14.3 percent of the E coli
they found appeared to be expect given
that E coli can be found in about 90
percent of retail turkey and chicken
products that would mean the industry
would have to dump literally billions of
pounds of chicken breasts every year
[Music]
thank you